This is my kitchen table and also my
filing system.
Over much of the past three decades,
I've been an investor the highest
calling of mankind.
I've often thought was private equity.
And then I started interviewing.
Oh, I watch your interview.
Those I know how to do something.
I've learned in doing my interviews, how
leaders make it to the top.
I asked him how much he wanted.
He said to 50.
I said, Fine.
I didn't negotiate with him.
I didn't know due diligence.
I have something I'd like to sell and
how they stay there.
You don't feel inadequate now because
being only the second wealthiest man in
the world, is that right?
One of America's most experienced
financial service executives is Charlie
Sharp.
He's currently the CEO and chairman of
Wells Fargo.
Previously had served as CEO of Visa and
CEO of CNY Mellon.
He's also held senior positions at
JPMorgan and Citicorp.
Recently, I had a chance to sit down
with Charlie Scharf.
Meet with him in Washington, D.C., to
talk about his extraordinary career.
Right now, the Federal Reserve has a
chairman, Jay Powell.
And obviously, there's some
dispute about whether he should be
investigated or not, least in the view
of the of the president.
What is the view of the banking
community?
You think the Fed's independence is
being compromised?
The independence of the Fed is
critically important, not just here in
the U.S., but in other parts of the
country.
And when you think about just the way
our our governing system works, you
know, it's different than a place like
China where there's long term
management, long term goals, high
coordination across all the different
areas of government.
You know, here we have, you know, a
political infrastructure that turns
over,
which has points of views, and we have a
more long term structure in place at the
Fed.
The committee vote is extremely
important.
And so, you know, creating the right
kind of balance between physical and
monetary policy to get to the best
outcome is extremely important.
There's no reason in my mind why the
president shouldn't have a point of
view.
All presidents have for a long period of
time.
They've done it in different ways.
This president does it very vocally in
terms of what his points of views are.
But even as it comes to, you know, who
he's choosing to nominate for the Fed,
you know, in this case, he's chosen
someone who has a point of view on
what's going on in the world, what it's
going to mean for jobs, what it's going
to mean for productivity.
And it's got to be
approved by Congress.
But this idea that there's total
separation is just not true.
But it is true when it gets to the
actual decision making.
Eventually the person nominated by the
president will be confirmed.
You think would be difficult for him to
lower interest rates at this point given
where the economy is.
Yeah, I think right now there's a pretty
clear consensus that it would be the
wrong thing to do until the Iran
conflict is clear, what the end is in
sight.
There's there's real risk out there.
Mean, I think as you hear voting
committee members talk about it, there's
a high degree of consistency, including,
I think, from the treasury secretary in
terms of, you know, waiting to see how
this all plays out.
And that seems like the prudent thing to
do.
What do you think the impact is on the
economy of the war today, right now?
From everything that we see, the economy
is still extremely strong.
We just we all just reported our first
quarter results in the banking space.
Loan demand is decent.
Delinquencies on the consumer side are
extremely well controlled.
Consumer spend is growing on a year over
year basis.
They're spending more money on gas.
But making adjustments in some of the
other categories, businesses have gone
into this in strong financial shape.
So those are all the good things.
But then when you ask them how they
feel, everyone's nervous.
And so, you know, they're not laying
off, but they're not hiring to the
extent that they would hire neutral to
just beginning to see some potential for
some negative impacts.
The real question is going to be is how
long does oil and gas prices stay high?
People always think about, you know, the
gas pump, but it's all these other
things that matter.
They're fine for a while because they
have long term contracts to buy some of
these things.
But that will come down the pike.
And if the conflict ends, the straights
open up, production returns in some
reasonable period of time.
There will be this impact on consumer
spend on some of these other things.
But in that kind of environment, it
won't be damaging.
If this goes on for a longer period of
time, it can be more damaging.
Is it better for banks generally have
interest rates go up or go down?
There's the short term impact and then
there's the longer term impact.
You know, we we have a lot of money
where we pay zero rates.
And so when what we earn falls, then
that squeezes our margins because we
can't lower zero.
What we pay customers 4.5 basis points.
Rising rate environment is certainly
helpful for something like that.
But what's most important is like what
are the reasons underlying it?
Because the amount of money that we'll
make in any given quarter from a
favorable interest rate curve for us is
de minimis compared to what it does to
the underlying base of our customers.
So if the economy is healthy, the
economy is growing, inflation's under
control, people are growing,
inventories, people are spending.
That's what's going to really drive
profitability for banks.
95% of our revenues come from the U.S.
We really live and breathe by the
success of the US customer in the US
business.
Are you worried about the value of the
dollar?
The dollar has gone down since President
Trump has been in office.
I think it's something we've got to be
conscious about.
You know the position the U.S.
dollar has in the world, we can't assume
that we just have this God given right
to be the reserve currency.
But it's going to take a long time for
people to get comfortable with something
else other than the dollar.
And it's in our control.
What about the US debt?
We have.
$39 trillion of debt.
And that's one of the issues that's got
to get solved because you've got people
who are in office for four, eight years.
They've got their own agenda on what
they want to accomplish.
They're not going to be there to solve
that problem.
And they don't have the same kinds of
immediate pressures that companies have
when they become overleveraged.
Recently, the concern has been in the
financial community about something
called private credit.
So is that legitimate concern?
Is private credit about to crumble in
some way?
No, I don't think private credit's about
to come crumbling.
When you look at private credit, when
you just look at the size of private
credit, it's not big enough to be a
systemic risk.
Broadly, the way we think about systemic
risks that existed in the past,
but it's credit.
And there's been a huge amount of money
that's flown into these products, both
institutional and retail.
And we've all seen this in the past when
there's just when there's a lot of money
that needs to get invested, because
that's the only way that these firms get
paid is to actually invest.
It doesn't always work out well.
And we're in an area where we've been in
this bull market for a long period of
time.
We haven't seen any recession
in over a decade.
You will see credit deterioration at
some point in time.
Has it changed your job very much that
you use Aon in running Wells Fargo?
I personally do.
We've enabled most of the company with
some of the basic tools, but we're at
the very beginning and, you know, we're
kind of going through pieces because
we've got to monitor it in a couple of
different ways.
Number one is how we use the tools
ourselves to either become more
efficient or deliver differentiated
products and services for our customers.
Number two is we learned a lot of money
to a lot of people.
And so understanding how A.I.
is going to impact their businesses
matters a lot to us.
And then we've got the question of just
like, how?
How's A.I.
going to change our business model?
We're most advanced in that order.
But we're towards the beginning of it.
But but it's incredibly powerful and
we're going to see meaningful benefits.
Revolut is a company with now a private
market value of $75 billion
headquartered in the U.K.
and now they're trying to get a U.S.
banking license.
Does that worry you as a potential
competitor to Wells Fargo and other
banks like yourself, that they could
build a whole banking system without any
bricks and mortar?
We think about the competitive
advantages that we have versus who we
compete with.
When you kind of step back and look over
the last ten or 15 years and say, you
know, what have the fintechs done to the
banking space?
I think first and foremost, it's made it
very clear to people who run banks that
the moats that have existed, that have
allowed you to move slowly
are no longer going to protect you.
In fact, you've got government and
regulators that are telling you you need
to do more.
So banks have woken up to the fact that
you have to compete not just with
regulated institutions, but
non-regulated institutions.
And we come at this with this great
position of strength, which is we have
trust,
we have the FDIC insurance, we have a
huge customer base.
When you're a big company, you sit and
look at small companies and say, Oh my
God, look how quick they can move the
great products.
They understand the customer.
All those things are true.
And then when you go to one of those
companies, you look at a company like us
and say they have 70 million customers.
And if they were to get some of these
things right, think about how hard it's
going to be for us to compete with them.
So it puts a huge amount of pressure on
us to have to deliver things in
different ways if we didn't have that
kind of competition.
But we know it's there.
So today on Wells Fargo, what is your
the market capitalization?
The market value today of Wells Fargo
is, what, 250, 260 billion.
Right.
And how many employees do you have?
200,000.
How many customers do you have?
70 million.
Wow.
That's a lot.
And what about credit cards?
You have a big credit cards, 20
something million cards.
Have you ever used a credit card and had
it denied?
One of
the truth.
Yes.
I get two wells and first thing I want
to do is get a Wells Fargo credit card.
And so I get the new card.
And I was out to dinner with some good
friends who run some big companies.
And I pull up my card and they got
tonight
that person in charge of that division
still there.
We've learned an awful lot.
It doesn't get to nine anymore, but
hasn't happened since.
Hasn't happened since.
Right.
What about the ATM business?
Is that a profitable business for banks?
The ATM business, it's marginally
profitable, but it's important.
It's convenience.
And, you know, it's cash is becoming
less important over a period of time.
People are able to deposit checks on
their phones and not having to go to
ATMs anymore.
But it's a little like branches.
You know, we can debate about, you know,
what the future is going to look like in
20 or 30 years.
But customers tell you what they want
and what they like and they like
convenience.
There's still plenty of cash that
circulates out there, especially in our
customer base.
And until they stop using ATMs, we're
going to still have them for them.
Let's talk about your background.
Where are you?
Where were you born?
I was born in Manhattan.
Raised in New Jersey.
What are your parents do?
My dad was with the time was called the
stockbroker.
Now we call it a financial advisor.
He worked till he was 77.
Loved the markets.
Still loves the markets.
My mom was a teacher because she wanted
to be able to be there when we came home
from school and then ultimately went to
work at AT&T and went into technology.
Where did you go to college?
Johns Hopkins.
I wanted to be a research chemist,
really.
And it's I loved science.
And in high school I loved math and I
love science.
My parents were always encouraging of
learning broad things and trying to find
what you wanted.
And both my brother and I were both very
much math and science people.
And I go to Hopkins and I first semester
I take organic chemistry where you're in
with all the Hopkins pre-med, which was
probably the worst experience of my
life.
All right.
So you said I want to be the head of a
bank.
No, banking was like not just not was
not there yet.
I said I want, like, a better education.
I want a much broader education.
And I just got convinced in talking to
people that college is this great
opportunity to learn a broad set of
things.
I've got nothing against business
schools or things like that, but you
know, there's plenty of time to learn
accounting.
Most of that stuff you learn on the job
anyway.
The college is a great example to learn
about international relations, political
science, psychology, sociology.
So I changed my major to what Hopkins
had this wonderful thing called social
and behavioral sciences area major,
where you were allowed to take a broad
set of classes and all those types of
things that I just said.
And I loved it.
I loved the people, I loved the
professors,
the students.
I love the work, and I think I'm a
better person for it.
So if you graduated one year.
I graduated college in 87.
And so I started going through all these
interview
programs, you know, the different
investment banks up in New York, because
I was from the New York area,
and then something else came along.
So you got a job at a place called
Commercial Credit, was young Guy was
working there.
Then Jamie Diamond, I think his name was
Jamie was 29, 30 years old at the time,
was CFO, played a really important role,
but he was one of like six or seven
really senior people.
And it was really over the next, you
know, three, four or five, six years
that Jamie asserted himself in terms of
what his capabilities were.
One of the things when I talk to younger
people all the time, I say, you know,
they always ask about, you know, who
role models and who do you learn the
most from?
And like for me, it's just being able to
see you think you can learn a whole lot
from someone who's the most successful,
but in reality, you learn.
Bits and pieces from different people
and figure out how it works for you.
How long were you and Jp morgan before
you?
I was there until 2012, so I got to Bank
one in 2000.
We so I started out as CFO, wound up
running the retail businesses for a
couple of years.
When we sold Bank One to Jp morgan, I
ran the retail businesses
until 2011 than a year in the private
equity business, and then I went to run
Visa and so we went to Visa.
But Visa is headquartered in San
Francisco and your family's in New York.
So my wife eventually moved out to
California.
Our kids were on the East Coast.
You say moved out.
She moved with you.
She moved
out.
She moved.
She came to join me.
Right.
Okay.
With with the dog.
We were all reunited in San Francisco.
And then it just became very clear for
personal reasons with one of my kids,
that we just couldn't be that far away.
Okay, so you moved back to the East
Coast.
So I left Visa without a job
and moved back to New York.
Why would you want to go to a bank that
can't grow?
How did they induce you to leave where
you were?
First, I was very hard to leave because
I was at Bank of New York Mellon, which
I went in maybe a year and a half before
I started these conversations.
And I didn't intend to leave.
I intended to stay there for the rest of
my career if they would have had me.
But I knew someone on the Wells Fargo
board from another board than a man, and
he was on me about you should engage
you.
You should engage.
You can be in New York.
We have a lot more in New York than you
think, which was important to me.
And then I just kind of go through what
Wells is.
And I competed against him for years.
And I believed and I believe today more
than ever, it's an incredibly important,
amazing financial institution in this
country,
which lost its way on a series of
things.
And if you sit there and say, if those
things are all fixable and someone were
to hand you the Wells Fargo franchise
that had been underperforming, that had
been restrained for for so long, that's
like a dream job.
So, you know, you got to take the risk
that you believe you can get through
these problems with the government, by
the way, in a difficult environment with
the Biden administration.
But if you come out on the other side,
it's incredibly exciting.
Before you came to Wells, they had a
problem and the wells was put under some
constraints by the federal government.
Yeah.
What were those constraints?
We had multiple constraints.
The biggest one that people
know about is we there was an asset cap
put in place.
So at the time I think it was 2018, we
were told that our assets at the time
were one point.
Nine five 2 trillion, and they couldn't
go higher than that until the consent
order work
was done to their satisfaction.
Well, how do you grow the company if you
can't grow your assets?
It's very, very hard.
So there are things you can't do in the
things you can do.
You've got to be, first of all, very
selective in looking at your balance
sheet and saying, okay, it's not the
worst thing in the world to say we need
to become more efficient on our balance
sheet.
What's less efficient where we make less
money?
How do we reallocate that balance sheet
usage?
You then turn to certain things and say,
we're just not going to be active about
soliciting loans.
We're not going to be active about
soliciting deposits.
We were very careful not to throttle
consumer deposits because you tell a
consumer to please bring your deposit
elsewhere and you've lost that
relationship.
Large corporates understand.
They understand we have an asset cap.
They understand we want to take their
money, but we just can't right now.
So we turned away massive amounts of
deposits at the time and we focused a
lot on businesses that drove fee based
revenues.
So we've grown our credit card business
dramatically, which includes a
significant portion of increasing the
spend.
We've grown our trading capabilities,
we've grown our investment banking
advisory capabilities.
We have our fee based treasury
management businesses.
And so you know that along with our
wealth management business, we get paid
on fees.
That's what we focused on.
What led to these sanctions.
Why did this happen?
There were a series of intra individual
things that the regulators identified.
They were right about them.
We can argue about whether the
punishment fit the crime, whether an
asset cap was the right thing to do for
a company like ours, but they weren't
wrong about the underlying issues.
And what happens is you get to the point
where if you're not resolving the issues
quickly enough, they say, okay, we need
to get your attention.
We're not getting your attention.
So the next step is you can't grow.
And so that's what they did.
We need banks of all sizes.
Our banks do have to scale with the
growth in the economy.
It doesn't mean that big versus small.
Both are necessary.
We do different things and and we try
and support small banks because we know
they play an incredibly important role.
Who?
You're in town, I guess, to meet
regulators and to meet members of
Congress.
How do you find that an uplifting
experience when you're meeting with
members of Congress are exciting?
I think it's incredibly important.
And I really dislike when people talk
about lobbying like it's some awful,
horrible thing showing up and trying to
convince a senator or a congressperson
at the last minute that what I think is
right.
When it's clear that it's just going to
benefit me goes nowhere.
What really matters is over a period of
time building a relationship with
members and their staffs, where you're
where you're honest about, about what
works, what doesn't work, what the risks
are.
And so that when they need to actually
have a position on something, they're
more educated.
And sometimes we agree on those things.
I mean, I mean, there are plenty of
members who I've got a huge amount of
respect for.
We don't agree on something, but it
doesn't mean I'm not going to talk to
them and it doesn't mean that we might
not agree on the next thing.
What is the biggest problem the United
States is facing now in the financial
service world?
We have uncertainty with what's going on
with the Iran conflict.
It's been a bull market for a long time.
There's a huge amount of liquidity in
the system.
There's this underlying current that
things are going to be fine for a long
period of time.
There are a lot of people in the
financial services space, in banks and
outside of banks that have never been
through cycles, like a real cycle in
terms of what that means.
And there's a point in which that's
going to turn and that's going to have a
whole bunch of impacts that I'm not sure
we all really understand something's
going to happen.
But then more long term, it's just the
question of the deficit.
Jp morgan City, Bank of America and
Wells Fargo.
Do you think only having four gigantic
banks is the right number?
We have 4000 banks in the country, and
when we think about financial services,
you really do have to think beyond banks
these days, right?
You talked about private credit.
$1.7 trillion of lending is now done
away from banks.
You've got all of the different things
that are being done in the private
equity space.
And so, you know, the definition of, you
know, what's done in the banking sphere
has changed very dramatically.
We need banks of all sizes.
We're not going to have branches in
every location.
We don't have the relationships that
they have, The standards that we have to
live with under when it comes to lending
are different than than small banks do.
If you're in a small bank in a local
community, I can I'll make a loan to you
based upon what I know about you.
I knew you as a kid.
I knew your parents.
I know you're going to pay me back.
I know exactly what you're going
through.
We can't do that.
The OCR is going to come in and they're
going to be pretty crazy.
No way.
So we need a broad cross-section of
banks to serve people locally.
We have big companies in this country
and we need big banks to do things for
those companies.
Netflix decides that it wants to enter
the bidding for a four Time Warner.
They call the in.
We were involved in the transaction.
We made a $30 billion commitment.
Those things have to get done if we're
going to continue to see the capital
markets activity.
And you need big banks to do that.
And if it's not us, it's going to be the
Europeans.
It's going to be the Japanese who were
coming back, ultimately the Chinese.
And so, you know, our banks do have to
scale with the growth in the economy.
It doesn't mean that big versus small.
Both are necessary.
We do different things and we try and
support small banks because we know they
play an incredibly important role.
So what is the most profitable part of
the business for big banks?
We have looked at all of the things we
do within Wells.
We've sold 22 businesses.
We did it to eliminate hobbies, to get
rid of things that we just weren't
interested in investing in.
We have four big lines of businesses
we're incredibly excited about.
All four.
All four have really strong returns,
have really great growth prospects, are
consumer deposit lending business.
It's our wealth management business
where we have 12,000 smart advisors
across the country.
It's our commercial bank where we've got
almost 15% share and a lot of the things
that we do and it's our corporate
investment bank, all of them have very
strong returns and strong opportunities
to grow and they fit together inside the
Wells Fargo franchise to allow us to
have just a greater breadth and greater
depth of what we can do for customers
who.